Guide to the C. C. Clay Papers, 1811-1925
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
C. C. Clay papers 1811-1925
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Clay, C. C. (Clement Claiborne), 1816-1882
20 Linear Feet 8,568 Items
Clement Claiborne Clay (1816-1882) was a lawyer, U. S. Senator, Confederate diplomat, and planter from Huntsville, Madison County, Alabama. He was married to Virginia Carolina (Tunstall) Clay (1825-1915). His father, Clement Comer Clay (1789-1866) was a U.S. Congressman and Governor of Alabama.
Collection includes personal, business, and political correspondence, accounts, diaries, memoranda, college notes, scrapbooks, and clippings of Clement Claiborne Clay, and of his father, Clement Comer Clay; his mother, Susanna Claiborne Withers Clay; his wife, Virginia Caroline Tunstall Clay; and brothers, Hugh Lawson Clay and John Withers Clay. Letters deal with family matters, including Alabama and Washington, D.C., social life, education, the management of cotton plantations, civic affairs in Huntsville; state and national politics and elections; Clay Sr.'s governorship; Clay Jr.'s service in both the U.S. and Confederate senates; ante-bellum politics; the organization of the Confederacy; Reconstruction politics, including Clay Jr.'s arrest, imprisonment, and his wife's efforts to obtain his release; Clay Jr.'s efforts to retrieve his property and re-establish farming operations, and to settle his father's estate; Virginia Clay's dissatisfaction with Reconstruction period social life, her tour of Europe, 1884-1885, and her efforts to operate the plantation after her husband's death.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The C. C. Clay Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift from 1933 to 1958.
Collection Overview
Personal, business, and political correspondence, accounts, diaries, memoranda, college notes, scrapbooks, and clippings of Clement Claiborne Clay (1816-1882), lawyer, U.S. senator, Confederate diplomat, and planter; of his father, Clement Comer Clay (1789-1866), lawyer, planter, U.S. congressman and senator, and governor of Alabama; of his mother, Susanna Claiborne (Withers) Clay (1798-1866); of his wife, Virginia Caroline (Tunstall) Clay (1825-1915), who wrote A Bell of the Fifties: Memoirs of Mrs. Clay, of Alabama, covering Social and Political Life in Washington and the South, 1853-1866: Put into Narrative Form by Ada Sterling (New York: Doubleday, 1904); and of his brothers, Hugh Lawson Clay and John Withers Clay, and of their wives.
Letters deal with family matters, including education of the elder Clay's three sons at the University of Alabama, Tuscaloosa, and the University of Virginia, Charlottesville; management of two or more cotton plantations and approximately fifty slaves; civic affairs in Huntsville; state politics, 1819-1860; Democratic and Whig party alignments, rivalries, and disputes; presidential elections, especially in 1844, 1852, and 1856; Clement Comer Clay's governorship, 1835-1837. the Creek War, 1836; the panic of 1837, Clement Claiborne Clay's election as a Democrat to the U.S. Senate in 1853 and his reselection in 1857. Other political matters referred to include the Compromise of 1850; Kansas-Nebraska difficulty; break with Stephen A. Douglas; Democratic Convention of 1860; secession; and organization of the Confederate government. Personal letters refer to social life in Alabama and in Washington, D.C.; visits to springs and health resorts; and Clement Claiborne Clay's travels for his health through Florida, 1851, and later to Arkansas and Minnesota.
Subjects of the Civil War years include Clement Claiborne Clay's political activities in the Confederate States Senate; his relations with Jefferson Davis; Federal raids on and occupation of Huntsville, consequent disruption of civilian life, and demoralization of slaves; J. W. Clay's publication of the Huntsville Democrat in various towns; Clay's defeat in the election of 1863 for the Confederate Senate; his and other agents' work in Canada, assisting in the return of escaped Confederate prisoners to Confederate territory; plots of a general revolt in the Northwestern states designed to join these states to the Confederacy; the Democratic Convention of 1864; Horace Greeley's efforts for peace, 1864; plans and execution of the Confederate raid on St. Albans, Vermont, 1864; Clay's return from Canada, and the final days of the Confederacy.
Material relating to the aftermath of the Civil War concerns accusations against Clay for complicity in Lincoln's assassination, Clay's surrender to Federal authorities, his imprisonment at Fortress Monroe, Virginia, and the efforts of Virginia (Tunstall) Clay to obtain her husband's release. Papers for the period 1866-1915 generally pertain to personal matters, principally Clay's poverty, his attempts to retrieve his confiscated property, the settlement of his father's estate, efforts to re-establish farming operations, and his years in the insurance business, 1871-1873, with Jefferson Davis; and Virginia (Tunstall) Clay's dissatisfaction with a restricted social life, her tour of Europe, 1884-1885, and her efforts in later years to operate the plantation. There are occasional references to political affairs.
The volumes consist of an executor's book of the estate of C. C. Clay, Sr., 1866-1869; letter books, 1864-1865; letterpress copy covering insurance business; memorandum books, 1853-1864, containing a mailing list of constituents and other notations; notebook, 1835-1841, containing college lecture notes; receipt books; legal fee book, 1814-1815; scrapbooks, ca. 1848-1903, one of which contains plantation accounts, 1870-1873, and minutes of the Madison County Bible Society, 1820-1830; and the diaries and scrapbooks, 1859-1905, of Virginia (Tunstall) Clay.
Correspondents include Jeremiah S. Black, E. C. Bullock, C. C. Clay, Sr., C. C. Clay, Jr., David Clopton [Virginia (Tunstall) Clay's second husband], W. W. Corcoran, J. L. M. Curry, Jefferson Davis, Varina Davis, Benjamin Fitzpatrick, U. S. Grant, Andrew Johnson, L. Q. C. Lamar, Clifford Anderson Lanier, Sidney Lanier, Stephen R. Mallory, Nelson A. Miles, James K. Polk, John H. Reagan, R. B. Rhett, E. S. Shorter, Leroy P. Walker, Louis T. Wigfall, and William L. Yancey.
Description above taken from Guide to Cataloged Collections in the Manuscripts Department of the William R. Perkins Library, Duke University (1980)
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Clay, Clement Comer, 1789-1866
Clay, John Withers
Clay, Hugh Lawson
Clay, Susanna Claiborne Withers, 1798-1866
Clay-Clopton, Virginia, 1825-1915
Davis, Jefferson, 1808-1809
Governors -- Alabama
Cotton growing -- Alabama
Education -- Southern States
Fort Monroe (Va.)
Plantations -- Alabama
Reconstruction (U.S. history, 1865-1877) -- Alabama
Alabama -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865
Alabama -- Politics and government -- To 1865
Alabama -- Social life and customs
Confederate States of America -- Politics and government
United States -- Politics and government -- 19th century
United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865
Saint Albans (Vt.) -- History -- Raid, 1864
Slavery -- History
Washington (D.C.) -- Social life and customs
Related Material
Clement C. Clay papers, 1846-1972
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence Series, 1811-1925, (22 boxes)
  - Correspondence, 1811-1847 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1848-1857 April (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1857 May-1862 May (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1862 June-1864 September (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1864 October-1865 December (Box 5)
    Fragments written in prison, 1865-1866.
  - Correspondence, 1866 (Box 6)
    "Manufactured testimony" against Mr. Clay.
  - Correspondence, 1867-1871 June (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1871 July-1877 August (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1877 September-1881 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1882-1884 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, 1885 January-1888 October (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1888 November-1890 June (Box 12)
  - Correspondence, 1890 July-1892 June (Box 13)
  - Correspondence, 1892 July-1897 (Box 14)
  - Correspondence, 1898-1900 (Box 15)
  - Correspondence, 1901-1903 (Box 16)
  - Correspondence, 1904-1905 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence, 1906-1908 September (Box 18)
  - Correspondence, 1908 October-1911 May (Box 19)
  - Correspondence, 1911 June-1913 (Box 20)
  - Correspondence, 1914-1920s (Box 21)
  - Correspondence, 1900s and undated (Box 22)
- Bound Volumes Series, 1835-1903, (17 volumes)
  - Executor's Book (Estate of Clement Comer Clay), 1866-1869 (Volume S:692)
  - Letterbook, 1864 June 14-September 29 (Volume M:693)
    Correspondence from Canada. Copies of letters from C.C. Clay to: Judah Benjamin, Jefferson Davis, Horace Greeley, Slidell and Mason, George H. Pendleton, and S. R. Mallory.
  - Letterbook, 1865 June 30-November 23 (Volume M:694)
    Correspondence fom Fortress Monroe. Copies of letters sent to E. M. Stanton and Andrew Johnson from C. C. Clay and copies of letters sent to Jefferson Davis, Jeremiah Black, and Robert Toombs by Virginia C. Clay.
  - Letterpress copy book, 1871-1873 (Volume M:695)
  - Memorandum Book, 1853-1861 (Volume M:696)
    Mailing list for congressional documents
  - Memorandum Book, 1853-1864 (Volume M:697)
  - Notebook, 1835-1841 (Volume M:698)
    College, personal, and legal notes.
  - Receipt Book, 1860-1882 (Volume S:699)
  - Receipts, 1871-1873 (Volume S:700)
  - Scrapbook, circa 1866-1878 (Volume S:701)
  - Scrapbook, circa 1865-1890 (Volume L:702)
  - Scrapbook, circa 1866-1903 (Volume M:703)
  - Madison County (Ala.) Bible Society minutes, 1820-1830; and C. C. Clay Plantation accounts, 1870-1873 (Volume F:705)
  - Scrapbook, 1848-1853 (Volume L:706)
  - Fee book, 1814-1815 (Volume S:707)
  - Virginia Clay scrapbook, 1862-1896 (Volume L:718)
  - Virginia Clay scrapbook, 1886-1893 (Volume L:719)
- Other Papers Series, (6 boxes)
  - Genealogy (Box 23)
  - Miscellany
  - Addresses and writings of Mrs. Virginia Clay-Clopton
  - Addresses and writings of Mrs. Virginia Clay Clopton (Box 24)
  - Calling and gift cards (Box 25)
  - Photographs of members of Clay and related families (Box 26)
  - Printed material
  - Virginia Clay diary, 1859-1866
  - Addresses of C. C. Clay
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 27)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 28)
  - Virginia Clay diaries, 1865-1909, (6 volumes) (Box 29)